Lafayette mss., 1572-1939 LMC 2326
Lilly Library
- Manuscripts
  - Alphabetical
    - Death announcement of Jean Adrien Antoine Jules Jusserand, a member of The American Friends of Lafayette - Signed by Walter P. Gardner, President, undated; TDS (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - "Was Washington Two-Faced with Lafayette?" - Walter P. Gardner, undated; TDS (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - "A Remarkable Bit of History - Washington and La Fayette" - Clement Sulivane, undated; TDS 3 p. (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Apology note - WPG, undated (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Lord Alan Gardner (Admiral) - Signature, undated; ADS on scrapbook page (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - John Campbell, Earl of Loudoun - signature, undated (Ovflat 30)
    - John Gaillard - Signature, undated; ADS on scrapbook page (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Stéphanie Félicité, comtesse de Genlis, to Monsieur Hayley, undated; AD 2 p. (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Stéphanie Félicité, comtesse de Genlis, to ?, undated; ADS 2 p. (Box 4, Folder 31)
      Unclear why this is in the undated section
    - George II - Signature and etching, undated; DS on scrapbook page (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - George IV, Prince of Wales - Signature, undated; Printed document signed (Box 4, Folder 31)
      "Signature of Prince of Wales acting as Prince Regent during the mental illness of his father, George III"
    - George IV - Signature, undated; Printed document signed (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Dr. Louis R. Gottschalk to WPG, undated; ADS (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Dr. Louis R. Gottschalk to WPG, undated; TD (Box 4, Folder 31)
      "Lafayette as commercial expert - Dr. Louis R. Gottschalk, of the University of Chicago, takes exception to the statement by Whitlock, Volume 1, page 280, "The mysteries of vulgar trade and commerce were beyond him (Lafayette) and he was compelled to write to Vergennes to ask what a free port was."
    - Maria Monroe Gouverneur to Mr. Fisher, undated; ADS (Box 4, Folder 31)
      "Maria Monroe Gouverneur - She was married in the White House in 1820, during her father's term as President. Her letter speaks of President Monroe as being 'very methodical.'"
    - Vice-Admiral Paul Guepratte - Salutations to Lindbergh, undated; ADS (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Alexander Hamilton to Caleb Swan, Paymaster-General - Pay warrant to Capt. Benyam in Williamson, for pay of the troops under the command of General Hamilton, undated; Printed document with autograph fill-ins, signed (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Virginia Harned to Mr. Palmer, undated; ADS 2 p. (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Unknown author - Manuscript account of the "Trouble in the Courts of the Tuileries", undated; ADS (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Julia Ward Howe - Signed engraving for Mr. George Dalton, undated; ADS (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Elbert Hubbard to W. P. Gardner, undated; ADS on scrapbook page (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - John Ireland, Archbishop of St. Paul, to Levi P. Morton, undated; ADS 2 p. (Box 4, Folder 31)
      Includes copy of photograph pasted on verso
    - Thomas Jefferson - Signature, undated; DS on scrapbook page (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Thomas Jefferson to Mr. Remsen, his secretary, undated; ADS (Box 4, Folder 31)
      "The Secretary of State and the President have an early session - Thomas Jefferson was appointed Secretary of State by President Washington, but did not enter upon his duties until March 27, 1790, John Jay, who had been Secretary for Foreign Affairs under the Confederation, holding over as Acting Secretary of State. Jefferson continued as Secretary in the second Washington Administration, serving until January 2, 1794. Mr. Remsen was Jefferson's Secretary. Later on he became the first President of the Bank of Manhattan Company, New York City."
    - Antoine Pierre Joseph Chapelle, Marquis de Jumilhac - "Memoire pour demander le riz pour le Regiment de Nouergue...", undated; ADS (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Alfred Huger - Annotated excerpts from "The Mercury", undated; TDS 2 p. with ADS note (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Charles Kemble to John Philip Kemble - Inscription, undated; ADS on scrapbook page (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Charles Kemble to Mr. Webster, undated; ADS (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Fanny Kemble - Signature, undated; Photostat (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - François Christophe de Kellermann, Duc de Valmy, to Madame La Motte, undated; ADS (Box 4, Folder 31)
      "Kellerman to Madame La Motte - Francois Christophe, Duc de Valmy (1735-1820). In 1792, as Major General, repulsed the Army of the Duke of Brunswick and delivered France by the famous "Cannonade of Valmy," for which victory he was later made the Duke of Valmy. In the meanwhile he was imprisoned by Robespierre on a charge of treason."
    - Viscount Gerard Lake - Signature, undated; DS on scrapbook page (Box 4, Folder 31)
      "Viscount Gerard Lake entered the British army at age of fourteen. After serving in Germany in the Seven Years' War, he came to America and commanded under Cornwallis. In 1800 was Commander in Chief of India. He was created a Viscount in 1807 and died in 1808 at age of 64."
    - Guillaume-Chrétien de Lamoignon de Malesherbes to Monsieur le Docteur Pierquin, undated; ADS 2 p. (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Henry Lee to ?, undated; ADS (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - W. R. Leech to WPG, undated; TD (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Francis Lewis - Signature, undated; DS on scrapbook page (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Philip II Livingston - Signature, undated; DS (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Alice M. Longfellow to "Sir", undated; ADS 2 p. (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Louise Longfellow to Mr. Abbott, undated; ADS 2 p. (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Leopold I of Belgium - Signed and addressed envelope, undated; ADS (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Henry W. Longfellow - Fragment, undated; ADS (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Samuel Longfellow to "Sir", undated; ADS 2 p. (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Benson J. Lossing - Signature, undated; DS on scrapbook page (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - James W. Henry, War Office - Signature, undated; DS on scrapbook page (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Mr. Macready to Mr. and Mrs. Bancroft - Invitation, undated; Printed document with autograph fill-ins (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Madame Marie Felicita Garcia de Malibran to Lafayette, undated; Photostat 2 p. (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Madame Marie Felicita Garcia de Malibran to Lafayette, undated; Photostat 2 p. (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Madame Marie Felicita Garcia de Malibran to Lafayette, undated; Photostat 2 p. (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Madame Marie Felicita Garcia de Malibran to Lafayette, undated; Photostat 4 p. (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Madame Marie Felicita Garcia de Malibran to Lafayette, undated; Photostat (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Marie Antoinette - Signature, undated; ADS (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Princess Mary, Daughter of George III, wife of Prince William Frederick, Duke of Gloucester, undated; ADS (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Newberry Port, MA, Committee of Correspondence - Manuscript resolution reacting against new taxes imposed on the Colonies and importation of tea from Britain, undated; ADS (Box 4, Folder 32)
      Includes bookseller's description and transcription
    - Memorandum on the discharge of Lord Cornwallis' parole, undated; Photostat 2 p. (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Merlin Antoine Christopher de Thionville to James Monroe, undated; Photostat 3 p. (Box 4, Folder 32)
      "Antoine Christophe Merlin de Thionville (1762-1833), a Revolutionist, member of the Legislative Assembly (1791-1792) and of the Convention (1792-1795), writes that he desires to take himself and his fortune to the only free country in the world. He desires to manufacture glass, which is to be cut in all sizes. He describes the state of the art, his means, the requirements for a good location and desires to know what are the probabilities of inducing others to invest and also as to the means of transportation, etc."
    - Thomas Mifflin - Signature and seal, undated; DS on scrapbook page (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Thomas Mifflin - Signature, undated; DS on scrapbook page (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Honore Gabriel Riqueti, Comte de Mirabeau - Minutes of a debate in which Mirabeau refers to certain lead mines, undated; AD (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Honore Gabriel Riqueti, Comte de Mirabeau - Fragment, undated; AD (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Sydney Owenson Morgan to Miss Caston (?), undated; ADS (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Sydney Morgan to Henry Chorley, undated; ADS 2 p. (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Sydney Morgan to Murriotte, undated; ADS (Box 4, Folder 32)
      "Lafayette's friend and correspondent - Lady Morgan - Sydney Owenson Morgan (1783-1859) was a noted Irish novelist. In 1812 she married Sir T. C. Morgan, M.D., who was later knighted in her interest. She visited La Grange and their correspondence ran over a period of many yeras, covering literature and politics."
    - Samuel F. B. Morse (painted Lafayette) - Fragment, undated; ADS (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Samuel F. B. Morse to John S. C. Abbott, undated; ADS (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Napoleon to Citoyen de Fumaye, Inspector of Food and Munitions, in the Army of Italy, General Headquarters at Milan, undated; ADS 2 p. (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - John Morton, William Parker, and James Moore - Certifying that Samuel Picken was imprisoned, undated; ADS (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Francois Muller to Louis Bonaparte (signed by both), undated; ADS (Box 4, Folder 32)
      "Louis Bonaparte (1778-1840) - third brother of Napoleon, received many honors, in 1806-1810 King of Holland (really Viceroy under his brother). Husband of Hortense Eugenie Beauharnais, who was a daughter of Josephine, afterward the second wife of Napoleon."
    - Sir Thomas Musgrave to George Yonge, undated; ADS (Box 4, Folder 32)
      "Sir Thomas Musgrave (1738-1812) became a Captain in the British Army in 1759, and was made Lieutenant Colonel of the 40th Regiment in August 1776, in which year he accompanied General Howe to America. He was wounded at the Battle of Pelham Manor October 1776, and at Germantown, October 4, 1777, saved the day by throwing himself with five companies into the Chew House, where he successfully held the American forced at bay until the British columns rallied. He was raised to the rank to General in 1802."
    - Napoleon - Signature as Premier Consul, also signed by Secretaire d'Etat, undated; Printed document signed, with seal (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Handwritten biography of the Vicomte de Noailles, Lafayette's sister-in-law's husband, undated; AD (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - E. B. D. Ogden - Signature, undated; ADS on scrapbook page (Box 4, Folder 32)
      "Associate Justice New Jersey Supreme Court, Elias Bailey Dayton Ogden - Son of Aaron Ogden, 1799-1865"
    - Aaron Ogden - Signature, undated; DS on scrapbook page (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Andrew Oliver - Fragment, undated; ADS (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - John Howard Payne to ?, undated; ADS 2 p. (Box 4, Folder 32)
      "The John Howard Payne leter was written in London. No date being given, I undertook to fix the same from the context of the letter. This I was unable to do, but I think that it may safely be said that the subject matter deals with his work in the period in which he produced "Home Sweet Home." At first I thought that his "little opera" to which he refers, might be "Clari" in which "Home Sweet Home" was first sung. There is some argument for this, as I find on page 106 of Harrison's Life of Payne he tells how, after Elliston of Drury Lane and Burroughs of the Surrey Theatre had gotten Payne into financial difficulties by their delays, there was a change in the management of Covent Garden, which came under the direction of Charles Kemble who sent word to Payne in Paris that he would like to secure his services..."
    - Timothy Pickering - Signature, undated; DS on scrapbook page (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Henri Pille - Military costume design sketches, undated; ADS (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Pius VII, Gregorio Chiaramonti - Document, undated; ADS (Box 4, Folder 32)
      "The Pope who excommunicated Napoleon - Gregorio Chiaramonti, Pius VII, was born in 1742 - made Pope in 1800 and died in 1823."
    - Pleville-le-Pelley to Monsieur le President du Senat - Asks to be excused from a session of the Senate on account of his swollen leg about which he is very disheartened, undated (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Charles de Pougens to Madame de... - Epistle in verse, undated; ADS (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - James Henry Rice, Jr. - "Where Lafayette Spent First Night", undated; TD 6 p. (Box 4, Folder 32)
      Includes manuscript note and annotations by Alfred Huger
    - Armand Emmanuel du Plessis, Duc de Richelieu, to ?, undated; ADS (Box 4, Folder 32)
      "A signer of the Treaty with the Allies - 1815. Armand Emmanuel du Plessis, Duc de Richelieu (1766-1822), a grandson of Marshal Richelieu and grand-nephew of the great Cardinal. He emigrated in 1789 and took service with Russia during the Revolution and Napoleonic period - he returned to France in 1814 and became Premier in 1815."
    - George Washington to John Robinson - Receipt, undated; ADS (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Nathan Meyer Rothschild - Signature, undated; DS (Box 4, Folder 32)
      "Nathan Meyer Rothschild (1777-1836), the son who was the head of the House of Rothschild in London. He staked his fortune on the success of Britain in her duel with Napoleon. He had private information of the result of the battle of Waterloo, and through his early information was able to make a tremendous profit on the London Stock Exchange."
    - Benjamin Rush - Fragment, undated; ADS on scrapbook page (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - John St. Clair, Quarter Master General - Fragment, undated; ADS (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Alexander Scammell - Fragment, undated; ADS (Box 4, Folder 33)
      "A victim of Yorktown - Alexander Scammell (1746-1781) was born in Massachusetts, graduated at Harvard in 1769 and studied law under John Sullivan who later became one of the important Generals of the Revolution. Scammell was one of the party under John Sullivan and John Langdon that captured Fort Williams and Mary, Newcastle, securing arms and 96 barrels of gunpowder. This was one of the first overt acts of the War and it was declared as treason, by the royal governor. He later became a Brigade Major and was wounded at Saratoga. He was then appointed Adjutant General of the Army and so became one of Washington's military family, but preferring active service he was given command of a regiment of light infantry and at Yorktown as Officer of the day, on September 30, 1781, while reconnoitering the enemy's position, he was captured by the Hessian Dragoons and wounded after his surrender. On request of General Washington he was permitted by General Cornwallis to be removed to Williamsburg, where he died."
    - Ary Scheffer to "Madame", undated; ADS 2 p. (Box 4, Folder 33)
      "Ary Scheffer (1795-1858), a German art student at Paris, first took up genre work, then became a Romantic and in later life turned to religious subjects. In 1817 he visited La Grange and there painted a full length portrait of Lafayette that has been so often reproduced in engravings."
    - Edward Shippen to "Sir", undated; ADS (Box 4, Folder 33)
      "Edward Shippen (1703-1781) was the father of Edward Shippen, the jurist. The father was the grandson of Edward Shippen (1639-1712) who came from England setled in Boston, but being a Quaker was forced to take refuge in Philadelphia and became one of its leading citizens. The grandson Edward was a prominent merchant in Pennsylvania - he acted as financial agent for supplies for the British and provincial troops prior to 1760. The above letter refers to some of his dealings with the Indians."
    - Signatures of French naval officers - Includes Bernard de Marigny, de Vaugniaute, de Monteil, de la Clochetevin, de Ridny, du Chattault, du Coudee, Borda, Chevalier de Fernay, de Suffren, Roquefuis, and others, undated; Several DS pasted on three scrapbook pages (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Anne Louise Germaine Necker, Madame de Stael, to ? (signed as Necker Stael de Holstein), undated; ADS 2 p. (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Col. John Stevens - Draft of Memorial to the Legislature of New York, for Railway, undated; TD 3 p. (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Col. John Stevens - A proposal for constructing Tunnels or Passsage-ways across the bed or bottom of Rivers, undated; TD 6 p. (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Col. John Stevens - Railroads-Construction, undated; TD 2 p. (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Col. John Stevens - Rail Ways and Steam Carriages, undated; TD 2 p. (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Thomas Sully to H. D. Gilpen, undated; ADS (Box 4, Folder 33)
      "Thomas Sully (1783-1872) - He was born in England and brought by his parents to the United States at the age of nine. He studied under his brother Laurence, a miniature-painter, but soon surpassed him in the art and then turned to oil portrait work. He advised with Gilbert Stuart in Boston and then went to London and studied under Benjamin West. Some of his famous paintings are "Washington Crossing the Delaware," "Bishop William White" of Pennsylvania, the picture of Lafayette now in Independence Hall, Philadelphia and the "Thomas Jefferson" in the U.S. Military Academy."
    - James Swan to Monsieur Dumenil de Merville, undated; ADS 2 p. (Box 4, Folder 33)
      "James Swan (1754-1831) took part in the Boston Tea Party and was wounded in the Battle of Bunker Hill while serving under General Warren. After the war he became involved in debt and went to France where he made a fortune, coming back to America and becoming noted for his benevolences. Again he went to Europe and in 1815 a suit was brought against him by a German merchant, Swan was put into jail in Paris and remained there fifteen years, meanwhile living in luxury and keeping alive the litigation. He was an author of some considerable note."
    - Prince de Talleyrand to Colard, undated; ADS 2 p. on scrapbook page (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Jean Baptiste de Ternant to Poirey, undated; ADS 2 p. (Box 4, Folder 33)
      "One of Lafayette's companions on the 'Victoire' - Jean de Ternant sailed with Lafayete in 1777 (see Balch, page 236). On his arrival in America, he did not at once enter the Army as he had some private commissions to execute. He joined Steuben's forces in March 1778, and Chastellux, in his Memoirs speaks well of Ternant, stating that he spoke English as well as he did French."
    - George Ticknor to the Librarian of Harvard College, undated; ADS (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - George Ticknor to "Sir", undated; ADS 2 p. (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Two receipts of payment by William Gardner, "Agent for paying Invalids in the State of New-Hampshire" - Signed by J. Trickney, undated; Printed document with autograph fill-ins, signed (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Mary C. Van Doorn (Mrs. Elbridge H. Van Doorn) to Henry D. Sedgwick, undated; ADS 2 p. (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Marshall Van Winkle - "That Great Litigation", with inscription from Van Winkle to WPG, undated; TD 4 p. on scrapbook page with ADS note (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - James M. Varnum - Signature, undated; DS on scrapbook page (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Admiral Edward Vernon to Richard (?), undated; ADS (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Pauline Garcia Viardot to "Monsieur", undated; ADS 2 p. (Box 4, Folder 33)
      "Pauline Garcia Viardot (1821-1910) was a singer as well as her sister the renowned Marie Malbran."
    - Queen Victoria - Signature, undated; DS on scrapbook page (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Henry Augustus Ward to Mr. Dorcel (?), undated; ADS (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - J. Wentworth - Excise Act in Province of New Hampshire, undated; ADS on scrapbok page (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - William Whipple - Signature, undated; DS on scrapbook page (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Illustration of Chateau de Chavaniac with notes by WPG - Includes handwritten note to Rutger (Bleecker Jewett) from Wand?, undated; TD with ADS (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Emma Willard - Note and signature, undated; ADS (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - William IV - Signature and seal, undated; Printed document signed (Box 4, Folder 33)
      "Third son of George III - William Henry, Duke of Clarence - 1763-1837 - after the death of his brother George IV, ruled as William IV - 1830-1837"
    - William Williams - Signature, undated; DS (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - James Wilson - Signature, undated; DS on scrapbook page (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Oliver Wolcott, Jr. - Signature and note that says "Mr. Antoine /has misbehaved/ again", undated (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Sgt. Alvin E. York - Signature, undated; DS (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Oversize, 1572-1935 (Ovflat 30)
- Facsimile and Printed
  - Facsimile and printed, 1067-1759 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Facsimile and printed, 1760-1775 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Facsimile and printed, 1776 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Facsimile and printed, 1777 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Facsimile and printed, 1778 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Facsimile and printed, 1779-1780 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Facsimile and printed, 1781 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Facsimile and printed, 1782-1786 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Facsimile and printed, 1787-1795 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Facsimile and printed, 1796-1804 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Facsimile and printed, 1805-1829 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Facsimile and printed, 1830-1936; undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Facsimile and printed correspondence, 1688-1837 (Ovflat 8)
  - Lafayette
    - Loose pamphlets and articles about Lafayette (Box 6)
    - Articles about Lafayette (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Exhibits (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Lafayette's calling card (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Clippings about Lafayette (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Genealogy (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Ribbons (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Printed and pictoral, "1824-1825" (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Unsorted printed (Box 7, 8, 9, 10)
  - B. F. Stevens, Facsimiles of Manuscripts in European Archives relating to America, 1773-1783 - Vol. 17, Nos. 1601-1613; 1625-1643 (Box 11)
  - A. Levasseur, Lafayette in America - unassambled print copy (Box 12)
- Pictures and Portraits
  - Portraits A-E (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Portraits F-K (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Portraits L-R (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Portraits S-Z (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Portraits of Lafayette (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Portraits - unidentified (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Boats and ships (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Buildings (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Costumes (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Declaration of Independence (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Maps (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Flags and seals (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous: U. S. (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous: France (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous: Great Britain (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Money and [illegible] (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Unordered scrapbook pages (Box 15, 16, 17)
  - Stamps and covers (Ovflat 8)
  - Pictures and printed (Ovflat 20)
- W. P. Gardner Memorabilia
  - Memorabilia, 1772-1926 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Memorabilia, 1927-1931 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Memorabilia, 1932-1954 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Memorabilia - A-Z, undated (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Photographs by W. R. Richardson (Box 18, Folder 5)